They're taking adventure to new lengths.
Tangled is a animation, family, adventure film directed by Byron Howard.
Feisty teenager Rapunzel, who has long and magical hair, wants to go and see sky lanterns on her
eighteenth birthday, but she's bound to a tower by her overprotective mother.
She strikes a deal with Flynn Rider, a charming wanted thief,
and the duo set off on an action-packed escapade.
Rapunzel (voice), played by Mandy Moore.
Flynn Rider (voice), played by Zachary Levi.
Mother Gothel (voice), played by Donna Murphy.
Stabbington Brother (voice), played by Ron Perlman.
Captain of the Guard (voice), played by M.C. Gainey.
Big Nose Thug (voice), played by Jeffrey Tambor.
Tangled is a 2010 American animated musical fantasy comedy film loosely based on the
German fairy tale "Rapunzel", and produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios.
Directed by Nathan Greno and Byron Howard, and written by Dan Fogelman,
it stars Mandy Moore, Zachary Levi, and Donna Murphy.
The film tells the story of Rapunzel, a young princess with magical
long blonde hair who tries to leave her secret tower.
She accepts the aid of an intruder, the outlaw Flynn Rider, to take
her out into the world which she has never seen.
Originally conceived and proposed by Disney animator Glen Keane in 2001, Tangled spent six years in production at a cost that has been estimated at $260
million, which, if accurate, would make it the most expensive animated feature film ever made and one of the most expensive films of all time.
The film employed a unique artistic style by blending together features of computer-generated imagery (CGI) and
traditional animation while using non-photorealistic rendering to create the impression of a painting.
Composer Alan Menken, who had collaborated on prior Disney animated features, returned to
score Tangled, and also wrote the film's songs with lyricist Glenn Slater.
Before the film's release, its title was changed from Rapunzel to
Tangled, reportedly to market the film gender-neutrally.
Tangled premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Los Angeles on November 14,
2010, and was released on November 24 by Walt Disney Pictures.
The film earned $592 million and became the
eighth-highest-grossing film of 2010.
Tangled received positive reviews from critics, with particular praise for the animation, and was
nominated for several awards, including Best Original Song at the 83rd Academy Awards.
It was Richard Kiel's last film role before he died in 2014.
Tangled spawned a franchise, including a short film, Tangled Ever After (2012), a video
game, a stage musical, and a television series which premiered in 2017.
A live-action adaptation is in development.
The film explores themes of princess, magic, hostage, fairy tale, horse.
The tone is uplifting.